<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Security on Zen 3.1</title>
    <link>http://zhen.org/categories/security/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Security on Zen 3.1</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Jian Zhen. All Rights Reserved.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 22 Mar 2015 09:57:56 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://zhen.org/categories/security/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Analyzing Security Trends Using RSA Exhibitor Descriptions</title>
      <link>http://zhen.org/blog/analyzing-security-trends-using-rsa-exhibitor-descriptions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Mar 2015 09:57:56 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://zhen.org/blog/analyzing-security-trends-using-rsa-exhibitor-descriptions/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The data used for this post is available &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/topclouds/rsaconf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. A word of warning, I only have complete data set for 2014 and 2015. For 2008-2013, I have what I consider to be representative samples. So please take the result set with a big bucket of salt.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After going through this analysis, the big question I wonder out loud is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How can vendors differentiate from each other and stand above the crowd when everyone is using the same words to describe themselves?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The annual security conference, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rsaconference.com/events/us15&#34;&gt;RSA 2015&lt;/a&gt;, is right around the corner. Close to 30,000 attendees will descend into &lt;a href=&#34;http://moscone.com&#34;&gt;San Francisco Moscone Center&lt;/a&gt; to attend 400+ sessions, listen to 600+ speakers and talk to close to 600 vendors and exhibitors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, the most interesting aspect of RSA is walking the expo floor, and listening to how vendors describe their products. Intuitively, the vendor marketing messages should have a high degree of correlation to what customers care about, even if the messages trail the actual pain points slightly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post highlights some of the unsurprising findings from analyzing 8 years worth of RSA Conference exihibitor descriptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is interesting how almost all vendor descriptions use the same set of words to describe themselves, and these words mostly haven&amp;rsquo;t changed over the past 8 years. For example, the following table shows the top 10 words used in RSA conference exhibitor descriptions for the past 8 years. You can find the complete word list at &amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;#&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;2008&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;2009&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;2010&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;2011&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;2012&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;2013&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;2014&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;2015&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;

&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;secure&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;secure&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;secure&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;secure&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;secure&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;secure&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;secure&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;secure&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;solution&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;solution&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;solution&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;solution&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;solution&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;solution&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;solution&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;solution&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;network&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;manage&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;manage&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;network&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;provide&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;provide&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;provide&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;provide&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;provide&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;provide&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;network&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;provide&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;manage&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;manage&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;network&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;data&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;manage&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;data&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;protect&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;manage&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;network&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;service&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;manage&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;network&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;enterprise&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;network&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;provide&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;data&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;information&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;more&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;data&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;protect&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;data&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;company&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;data&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;information&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;software&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;software&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;protect&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;threat&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;product&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;service&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;organization&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;enterprise&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;enterprise&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;information&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;threat&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;manage&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;technology&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;software&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;information&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;technology&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;data&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;enterprise&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;service&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;service&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;application&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;busy&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;risk&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;product&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;more&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;customer&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;enterprise&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;enterprise&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a word cloud that shows the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/topclouds/rsaconf/blob/master/rsa2015.png&#34;&gt;2015&lt;/a&gt; top words. You can also find word clouds for
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/topclouds/rsaconf/blob/master/rsa2008.png&#34;&gt;2008&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/topclouds/rsaconf/blob/master/rsa2009.png&#34;&gt;2009&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/topclouds/rsaconf/blob/master/rsa2010.png&#34;&gt;2010&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/topclouds/rsaconf/blob/master/rsa2011.png&#34;&gt;2011&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/topclouds/rsaconf/blob/master/rsa2012.png&#34;&gt;2012&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/topclouds/rsaconf/blob/master/rsa2013.png&#34;&gt;2013&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/topclouds/rsaconf/blob/master/rsa2014.png&#34;&gt;2014&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://zhen.org/images/rsaconf/rsa2015.png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;compliance-down-threats-up:b082a5c20b5449f4372a8955a4b5d0dd&#34;&gt;Compliance Down, Threats Up&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the macro trend has not changed dramatically for the exhibitor descriptions, there have been some micro trends. Here are a couple of examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the use of the word &lt;em&gt;compliance&lt;/em&gt; has gone down over the years, while the word &lt;em&gt;threat&lt;/em&gt; has gone up. After 2013, they changed places with each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This finding is probably not surprising. At the end of 2013, one of the biggest breaches, Target, happened. And over the next two years we&amp;rsquo;ve seen major breaches of Sony, Anthem, Home Depot, Premera and many others. Threats to both the corporate infrastructure as well as top executive jobs (just ask &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.forbes.com/sites/ericbasu/2014/06/15/target-ceo-fired-can-you-be-fired-if-your-company-is-hacked/&#34;&gt;Target’s CEO Gregg Steinhafel&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href=&#34;http://abcnews.go.com/Entertainment/wireStory/sony-chief-amy-pascal-acknowledges-fired-28918607&#34;&gt;Sony&amp;rsquo;s Co-Chairwoman Amy Pascal&lt;/a&gt;) are becoming real. So it seems natural for the marketers to start using the word &lt;em&gt;threat&lt;/em&gt; to highlight their solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Compliance&lt;/em&gt; was a big use case in security for many years, and many vendors have leveraged the need for compliance to build their company and revenue pipeline since the mid-2000s. However, use cases can only remain in fashion for so long before customers get sick of hearing about them, and vendors need new ways of selling their wares to customers. So it looks like &lt;em&gt;compliance&lt;/em&gt; is finally out of fashion around 2011 and started declining in exhibitor descriptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://zhen.org/images/rsaconf/compliance-threat.png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;mobile-and-cloud-up:b082a5c20b5449f4372a8955a4b5d0dd&#34;&gt;Mobile and Cloud Up&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The words &lt;em&gt;mobile&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;cloud&lt;/em&gt; has gained dramatically in rankings over past 8 years. In fact, it&amp;rsquo;s been consistently one of the top words used in the last 4. For anyone who hasn&amp;rsquo;t been hiding under a rock in the past few years, this is completely unsurprising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;cloud&lt;/em&gt; war started to heat up back in 2009 when most major service providers have felt the Amazon Web Services threat and all wanted to build their own clouds. In fact, I joined VMware in 2009 to build out their emerging cloud infrastructure group to specifically help service providers build their cloud infrastructures. Eventually, in 2011, VMware decided to get into the game and I built the initial product and engineering team that developed what it&amp;rsquo;s now known as vCloud Air (still have no idea why this name is chosen).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As more and more workloads move to the cloud, requirements for protecting cloud workloads quickly appeared, and vendors natually started to position their products for the cloud. So the rise in &lt;em&gt;cloud&lt;/em&gt; rankings matches what I&amp;rsquo;ve experiened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About the same time (2010, 2011 or so), more and more corporations are providing their employees smartphones, and workers are becoming more and more mobile. The need for mobile security became a major requirement, and a whole slueth of mobile security startup came into the scene. So natually the &lt;em&gt;mobile&lt;/em&gt; word rose in rankings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://zhen.org/images/rsaconf/mobile-cloud.png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;virtual-and-real-time-regaining-ground:b082a5c20b5449f4372a8955a4b5d0dd&#34;&gt;Virtual and Real-Time Regaining Ground&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The words &lt;em&gt;virtual&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;real-time&lt;/em&gt; dropped dramatically in rankings for a couple of years (2010, 2011) but have since regained all the lost ground and more. I have no precise reasons on why that&amp;rsquo;s the case but I have some theories. These theories are probably completely wrong, and if you have better explanations I would love to hear from you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Virtual&lt;/em&gt; lost to &lt;em&gt;cloud&lt;/em&gt; during that timeframe as every vendor is trying to position their products for the cloud era. However, &lt;em&gt;virtual&lt;/em&gt; infrastructures haven&amp;rsquo;t gone away and in fact continue to experience strong growth. So in the past couple of years, marketers are covering their basis and starting to message both &lt;em&gt;virtual&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;cloud&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The drop in rankings for &lt;em&gt;real-time&lt;/em&gt; is potentially due to the peak of &lt;em&gt;compliance&lt;/em&gt; use case, which is usually report-based and does not have &lt;em&gt;real-time&lt;/em&gt; requirements. Also, I suspect another reason is that SIEM, which &lt;em&gt;real-time&lt;/em&gt; is critical, is going out of fashion somewhat due to the high cost of ownership and lack of trust in the tools. However, given the recent rise of &lt;em&gt;threats&lt;/em&gt;, natually &lt;em&gt;real-time&lt;/em&gt; becomes critical again.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://zhen.org/images/rsaconf/virtual-real-time.png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;other-findings:b082a5c20b5449f4372a8955a4b5d0dd&#34;&gt;Other Findings&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The word &lt;em&gt;cyber&lt;/em&gt; gained huge popularity in the past 3 years, likely due to the U.S. government&amp;rsquo;s focus on &lt;em&gt;cyber&lt;/em&gt; security. The word &lt;em&gt;malware&lt;/em&gt; has been fairly consistently at the top 100 words since 2010.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://zhen.org/images/rsaconf/cyber-malware.png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The words &lt;em&gt;product&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;service&lt;/em&gt; switched places in 2013, likely due to the increase in number of security software-as-a-service plays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://zhen.org/images/rsaconf/product-service.png&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;credits:b082a5c20b5449f4372a8955a4b5d0dd&#34;&gt;Credits&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The word clouds and word rankings are generated using &lt;a href=&#34;http://timdream.org/wordcloud&#34;&gt;Word Cloud&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The actual vendor descriptions are gathered from the RSA web site as well as press releases from Business Wire and others.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Charts are generated using Excel, which continues to be one of the best friends for data analysts (not that I consider myself one).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Papers I Read: 2015 Week 8</title>
      <link>http://zhen.org/blog/papers-i-read-2015-week-8/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Feb 2015 19:57:56 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://zhen.org/blog/papers-i-read-2015-week-8/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h3 id=&#34;random-ramblings:29724b4ec2d333ad12e89fd98257dccd&#34;&gt;Random Ramblings&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another week, another report of hacks. This time, &lt;a href=&#34;http://securelist.com/blog/research/68732/the-great-bank-robbery-the-carbanak-apt/&#34;&gt;The Great Bank Robbery&lt;/a&gt;, where up to 100 financial institutions have been hit.Total financial losses could be as a high as $1bn. You can download the &lt;a href=&#34;http://25zbkz3k00wn2tp5092n6di7b5k.wpengine.netdna-cdn.com/files/2015/02/Carbanak_APT_eng.pdf&#34;&gt;full report&lt;/a&gt; and learn all about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sony spent $15M to clean up and remediate their hack. I wonder how much these banks are going to spend on tracing the footsteps of their intruders and trying to figure out exactly where they have gone, what they have done and what they have taken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t make much progress this week on either &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/strace/sequence&#34;&gt;sequence&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/surgemq/surgemq&#34;&gt;surgemq&lt;/a&gt; because of busy work schedule and my son getting sick AGAIN!! But I did merge the few surgemq &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/surgemq/surgemq/pulls?q=is%3Apr+is%3Aclosed&#34;&gt;pull requests&lt;/a&gt; that the community has graciously contributed. One of them actually got it tested on Raspberry! That&amp;rsquo;s pretty cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also did manage to finish up the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/strace/sequence/commit/713979f70d6025308e434205973249aa3138e58e&#34;&gt;experimental json scanner&lt;/a&gt; that I&amp;rsquo;ve been working on for the past couple of weeks. I will write more about it in the next &lt;a href=&#34;http://strace.io/sequence&#34;&gt;sequence&lt;/a&gt; article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually I am starting to feel a bit overwhelmed by having both projects. Both of them are very interesting and I can see both move forward in very positive ways. Lots of ideas in my head but not enough time to do them. Now that I am getting feature requests, issues and pull requests, I feel even worse because I haven&amp;rsquo;t spent enough time on them. &amp;lt;sigh&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;papers-i-read:29724b4ec2d333ad12e89fd98257dccd&#34;&gt;Papers I Read&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pdl.cmu.edu/PDL-FTP/HECStorage/git-cercs-12-08.pdf&#34;&gt;Memory-Efficient GroupBy-Aggregate using Compressed Buffer Trees&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Memory is rapidly becoming a precious resource in many data processing environments. This paper introduces
a new data structure called a Compressed Buffer Tree (CBT). Using a combination of buffering, compression,
and lazy aggregation, CBTs can improve the memoryefficiency of the GroupBy-Aggregate abstraction which
forms the basis of many data processing models like MapReduce and databases. We evaluate CBTs in the
context of MapReduce aggregation, and show that CBTs can provide significant advantages over existing hashbased
aggregation techniques: up to 2× less memory and 1.5× the throughput, at the cost of 2.5× CPU.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.usenix.org/system/files/conference/atc14/atc14-paper-hu.pdf&#34;&gt;ELF: Efficient Lightweight Fast Stream Processing at Scale&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stream processing has become a key means for gaining rapid insights from webserver-captured data. Challenges
include how to scale to numerous, concurrently running streaming jobs, to coordinate across those jobs to share
insights, to make online changes to job functions to adapt to new requirements or data characteristics, and for each job, to efficiently operate over different time windows. The ELF stream processing system addresses these new challenges. Implemented over a set of agents enriching the web tier of datacenter systems, ELF obtains scalability by using a decentralized “many masters” architecture where for each job, live data is extracted directly from webservers, and placed into memory-efficient compressed buffer trees (CBTs) for local parsing and temporary storage, followed by subsequent aggregation using shared reducer trees (SRTs) mapped to sets of worker processes. Job masters at the roots of SRTs can dynamically customize worker actions, obtain aggregated results for end user delivery and/or coordinate with other jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.kernel.org/pub/linux/kernel/people/paulmck/perfbook/perfbook.html&#34;&gt;Is Parallel Programming Hard, And, If So, What Can You Do About It?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not just a paper, it&amp;rsquo;s a whole book w/ 800+ pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this book is to help you program shared-memory parallel machines without risking your sanity.1 We hope that this book’s design principles will help you avoid at least some parallel-programming pitfalls. That said, you should think of this book as a foundation on which to build, rather than as a completed cathedral. Your mission, if you choose to accept, is to help make further progress in the exciting field of parallel programming—progress that will in time render this book obsolete. Parallel programming is not as hard as some say, and we hope that this book makes your parallel-programming projects easier and more fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Papers I Read: 2015 Week 7</title>
      <link>http://zhen.org/blog/papers-i-read-2015-week-7/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2015 19:57:56 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://zhen.org/blog/papers-i-read-2015-week-7/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;random-ramblings:10248ddcf524aa32198bc5cded1aa098&#34;&gt;Random Ramblings&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, another week, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2015/02/05/business/hackers-breached-data-of-millions-insurer-says.html&#34;&gt;another big data breach&lt;/a&gt;. This time is Anthem, one of the nation’s largest health insurers. Ok, maybe it was last week that it happend. But this week they revealed that &lt;a href=&#34;http://consumerist.com/2015/02/13/anthem-says-data-from-as-far-back-as-2004-exposed-during-hack-offering-free-identity-theft-protection/&#34;&gt;hackers had access &amp;hellip; going back as far as 2004&lt;/a&gt;. WSJ blamed Anthem for &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wsj.com/articles/investigators-eye-china-in-anthem-hack-1423167560&#34;&gt;not encrypting the data&lt;/a&gt;. Though I have to agree with Rich Mogull over at Securosis that &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://securosis.com/blog/even-if-anthem-encrypted-it-probably-wouldnt-have-mattered&#34;&gt;even if Anthem had encrypted, it probably wouldn’t have helped&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel bad for saying this but there&amp;rsquo;s one positive side effect from all these data breaches. Security is now officially a boardroom topic. Anthem&amp;rsquo;s CEO, Joseph Swedish, is now &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.latimes.com/business/la-fi-anthem-hack-ceo-20150213-story.html#page=1&#34;&gt;under the gun&lt;/a&gt; because top level executives are no longer immune to major security breaches that affect the company&amp;rsquo;s top line. Just ask &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.forbes.com/sites/ericbasu/2014/06/15/target-ceo-fired-can-you-be-fired-if-your-company-is-hacked/&#34;&gt;Target’s CEO Gregg Steinhafel&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href=&#34;http://abcnews.go.com/Entertainment/wireStory/sony-chief-amy-pascal-acknowledges-fired-28918607&#34;&gt;Sony&amp;rsquo;s Co-Chairwoman Amy Pascal&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brian Krebs wrote a &lt;a href=&#34;http://krebsonsecurity.com/2015/02/anthem-breach-may-have-started-in-april-2014/&#34;&gt;detailed piece&lt;/a&gt; analyzing the various pieces of information available relating to the Anthem hack. Quite an interesting read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One chart in the artile that Brian referred to is the time difference between the “time to compromise” and the “time to discovery&amp;rdquo;, taken from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.verizonenterprise.com/DBIR/2014/&#34;&gt;Verizon’s 2014 Data Breach Investigations Report&lt;/a&gt;. As Brian summaries, &amp;ldquo;TL;DR: That gap is not improving, but instead is widening.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What this really says is that, &lt;strong&gt;you will get hacked&lt;/strong&gt;. So how do you shorten the time between getting hacked, and finding out that you are hacked so you can quickly remediate the problem before worse things happen?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/timetocompromise.png&#34; alt=&#34;The time difference between the “time to compromise” and the “time to discovery.”&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all these data breaches as backdrop, this week we also saw &amp;ldquo;President Barack Obama signed an executive order on Friday designed to spur businesses and the Federal Government to share with each other information related to cybersecurity, hacking and data breaches for the purpose of safeguarding U.S. infrastructure, economics and citizens from cyber attacks.&amp;rdquo; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://gigaom.com/2015/02/13/obamas-executive-order-calls-for-sharing-of-security-data/&#34;&gt;Gigaom&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general I don&amp;rsquo;t really think government mandates like this will work. The industry has to feel the pain enough that they are willing to participate, otherwise it&amp;rsquo;s just a waste of paper and ink. Facebook seems to be taking a lead in security information sharing and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/notes/protect-the-graph/threatexchange-sharing-for-a-safer-internet/1566584370248375&#34;&gt;launched their ThreatExchange security framework&lt;/a&gt; this week. along with Pinterest, Tumblr, Twitter, and Yahoo. Good for them! I hope this is not a temporary PR thing, and that they keep funding and supporting the framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;papers-i-read:10248ddcf524aa32198bc5cded1aa098&#34;&gt;Papers I Read&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another great resource of computer science papers is Adrian Coyler&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.acolyer.org/&#34;&gt;the morning paper&lt;/a&gt;. He selects and summarizes &amp;ldquo;an interesting/influential/important paper from the world of CS every weekday morning&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.put.poznan.pl/dweiss/site/publications/download/fsacomp.pdf&#34;&gt;Smaller Representation of Finite State Automata&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I read this paper when I was trying to figure out how to make the FSAs smaller for the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/surge/xparse/tree/master/etld&#34;&gt;Effective TLD matcher&lt;/a&gt; I created. The FSM I generated is 212,294 lines long. That&amp;rsquo;s just absolutely crazy. This paper seems to present an interesting way of compressing them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not exactly sure if &lt;a href=&#34;https://godoc.org/golang.org/x/net/publicsuffix&#34;&gt;PublicSuffix&lt;/a&gt; uses a similar representation but it basically represents a FSA as an array of bytes, and then walk the bytes like a binary search tree. It&amp;rsquo;s interesting for sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper is a follow-up to Jan Daciuk’s experiments on space-efficient finite state automata representation that can be used directly for traversals in main memory [4]. We investigate several techniques of reducing the memory footprint of minimal automata, mainly exploiting the fact that transition labels and transition pointer offset values are not evenly distributed and so are suitable for compression. We achieve a size gain of around 20–30% compared to the original representation given in [4]. This result is comparable to the state-of-the-art dictionary compression techniques like the LZ-trie [12] method, but remains
memory and CPU efficient during construction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://arxiv.org/pdf/1409.5942v1.pdf&#34;&gt;IP Tracing and Active Network Response&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This work presents integrated model for active security response model. The proposed model introduces Active Response Mechanism (ARM) for tracing anonymous attacks in the network back to their source. This work is motivated by the increased frequency and sophistication of denial-of-service attacks and by the difficulty in tracing packets with incorrect, or “spoofed”, source addresses. This paper presents within the proposed model two tracing approaches based on:
• Sleepy Watermark Tracing (SWT) for unauthorized access attacks.
• Probabilistic Packet Marking (PPM) in the network for Denial of Service
(DoS) and Distributed Denial of Service (DDoS) attacks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://static.googleusercontent.com/media/research.google.com/en/us/pubs/archive/36356.pdf&#34;&gt;Dapper, a Large-Scale Distributed Systems Tracing Infrastructure&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here we introduce the design of Dapper, Google’s production distributed systems tracing infrastructure, and describe how our design goals of low overhead, application-level transparency, and ubiquitous deployment on a very large scale system were met. Dapper shares conceptual similarities with other tracing systems, particularly Magpie [3] and X-Trace [12], but certain design
choices were made that have been key to its success in our environment, such as the use of sampling and restricting the instrumentation to a rather small number of common libraries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.confluent.io/2015/01/29/making-sense-of-stream-processing/&#34;&gt;STREAM PROCESSING, EVENT SOURCING, REACTIVE, CEP… AND MAKING SENSE OF IT ALL&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not a paper, but a good write up nonetheless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some people call it stream processing. Others call it Event Sourcing or CQRS. Some even call it Complex Event Processing. Sometimes, such self-important buzzwords are just smoke and mirrors, invented by companies who want to sell you stuff. But sometimes, they contain a kernel of wisdom which can really help us design better systems. In this talk, we will go in search of the wisdom behind the buzzwords. We will discuss how event streams can help make your application more scalable, more reliable and more maintainable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Papers I Read: 2015 Week 6</title>
      <link>http://zhen.org/blog/papers-i-read-2015-week-6/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Feb 2015 19:57:56 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://zhen.org/blog/papers-i-read-2015-week-6/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://paperswelove.org/&#34;&gt;Papers We Love&lt;/a&gt; has been making rounds lately and a lot of people are excited about it. I also think it&amp;rsquo;s kind of cool since I&amp;rsquo;ve been reading a lot of research papers over the past year or so. I have been killing some trees because of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My interests have been mostly around data analytics, but the specific focus areas have changed a few times. I have read papers on data structures (bloom filters, skiplist, bitmap compression, etc), security analytics, consumer behavioral analysis, loyalty analytics, and now back to security analytics. In fact, recently I started reading a few security research papers that I found on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.covert.io/&#34;&gt;covert.io&lt;/a&gt;, put together by Jason Trost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, I thought it might be an interesting idea to share some of the papers I read/scan/skim on weekly basis. This way I can also track what I read over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;random-ramblings:e2137c343047358d9912399632750231&#34;&gt;Random Ramblings&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week has been a disaster. I was the last one in the family to catch the cold, but probably lasted the longest. In fact I am still only about 50%. This whole week I have been having headaches, body aches, and haven&amp;rsquo;t been able to concentrate. My body must be trying to catch up on sleep or something. For a couple days I actually slept for almost 12 hours a night!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been meaning to work on &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/strace/sequence&#34;&gt;sequence&lt;/a&gt; and finish updating the analyzer, but really had a hard time concentrating. Any non-working hours are basically spent in bed if I could.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this is probably the worst week to start the &amp;ldquo;Papers I Read&amp;rdquo; series since I only technically read 1 paper. But I am going to cheat a little, and list the papers I read over the past couple of weeks, pretty much all in my spare time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week we also saw Sony&amp;rsquo;s accouncement that last year&amp;rsquo;s hack cost them &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sony.net/SonyInfo/IR/financial/fr/150204_sony.pdf&#34;&gt;$15 million&lt;/a&gt; to investigate and remediate. It&amp;rsquo;s pretty crazy if you think about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s assume that they hired a bunch of high-priced consultants, say $250/hour, to help comb through the logs and clean the systems. And let&amp;rsquo;s say &lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; of the $15m is spent on these consultants. That&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code&gt;$10m / $250 = 40,000 hours&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s say these consultants worked full time, non-stop, no weekends, no breaks, for 2 months since the announcement on Nov 24, 2014, that would be a team of 56 people (&lt;code&gt;40,000 hours / 60 days / 12 hours/day = 56&lt;/code&gt;) working 12 hour days!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll tell ya, these security guys are raking it in. They make money upfront by selling products/services to protect the company, then they make money in the back by selling forensic services to clean up after the hack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[Disclaimer: any mistake in my calculations/assumptions I blame on my drugged brain cells.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;papers-i-read:e2137c343047358d9912399632750231&#34;&gt;Papers I Read&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.covert.io/research-papers/security/Beehive%20-%20Large-Scale%20Log%20Analysis%20for%20Detecting%20Suspicious%20Activity%20in%20Enterprise%20Networks.pdf&#34;&gt;Beehive: Large-Scale Log Analysis for Detecting Suspicious Activity in Enterprise Networks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We present a novel system, Beehive, that attacks the problem of automatically mining and extracting knowledge from the dirty log data produced by a wide variety of security products in a large enterprise. We improve on signature-based approaches to detecting security incidents and instead identify suspicious host behaviors that Beehive reports as potential security incidents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://minds.cs.umn.edu/publications/chapter.pdf&#34;&gt;Data Mining for Cyber Security&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This chapter provides an overview of the Minnesota Intrusion Detection System (MINDS), which uses a suite of data mining based algorithms to address different aspects of cyber security. The various components of MINDS such as the scan detector, anomaly detector and the profiling module detect different types of attacks
and intrusions on a computer network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.covert.io/research-papers/security/VAST-%20Network%20Visibility%20Across%20Space%20and%20Time.pdf&#34;&gt;VAST: Network Visibility Across Space and Time&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Key operational networking tasks, such as troubleshooting and defending against attacks, greatly benefit from attaining views of network activity that are unified across space and time. This means that data from heterogeneous devices and systems is treated in a uniformfashion, and that analyzing past activity and detecting future instances follow the same procedures. Based on previous ideas that formulated principles for comprehensive
network visibility [AKP+08], we present the design and architecture of Visibility Across Space and Time (VAST), an intelligent database that serves as a single vantage point into the network. The system is based on a generic event model to handle network data from disparate sources and provides a query architecture that allows operators or remote applications to extract events matching a given condition. We implemented a proof-of-principle prototype that can archive and index events from a wide range of sources. Moreover, we conducted a preliminary performance evaluation to verify that our implementation works efficient and as expected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.covert.io/research-papers/security/Finding%20The%20Needle-%20Suppression%20of%20False%20Alarms%20in%20Large%20Intrusion%20Detection%20Data%20Sets.pdf&#34;&gt;Finding The Needle: Suppression of False Alarms in Large Intrusion Detection Data Sets&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Managed security service providers (MSSPs) must manage and monitor thousands of intrusion detection sensors.
The sensors often vary by manufacturer and software version, making the problem of creating generalized tools to separate true attacks from false positives particularly difficult. Often times it is useful from an operations perspective to know if a particular sensor is acting out of character. We propose a solution to this problem using anomaly detection techniques over the set of alarms produced by the sensors. Similar to the manner in which an anomaly based sensor detects deviations from normal user or system behavior, we establish the baseline
behavior of a sensor and detect deviations from this baseline. We show that departures from this profile by a sensor have a high probability of being artifacts of genuine attacks. We evaluate a set of time-based Markovian heuristics against a simple compression algorithm and show that we are able to detect the existence of all attacks which were manually identified by security personnel, drastically reduce the number of false positives, and identify attacks which were overlooked during manual evaluation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://user.informatik.uni-goettingen.de/~krieck/docs/2013a-aisec.pdf&#34;&gt;A Close Look on n-Grams in Intrusion Detection: Anomaly Detection vs. Classification&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Detection methods based on n-gram models have been widely studied for the identification of attacks and malicious software. These methods usually build on one of two learning schemes: anomaly detection, where a model of normality is constructed from n-grams, or classification, where a discrimination between benign and malicious n-grams is learned. Although successful in many security domains, previous work falls short of explaining why a particular scheme is used and more importantly what renders one favorable over the other for a given type of data. In this paper we provide a close look on n-gram models for intrusion detection. We specifically study anomaly detection and classification using n-grams and develop criteria for data being used in one or the other
scheme. Furthermore, we apply these criteria in the scope of web intrusion detection and empirically validate their effectiveness with different learning-based detection methods for client-side and service-side attacks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.scalyr.com/2014/05/searching-20-gbsec-systems-engineering-before-algorithms/&#34;&gt;Searching 20 GB/sec: Systems Engineering Before Algorithms&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, this is a blog post, not a research paper, but it&amp;rsquo;s somewhat interesting nonetheless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article describes how we met that challenge using an “old school”, brute-force approach, by eliminating layers and avoiding complex data structures. There are lessons here that you can apply to your own engineering challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Response to &#34;Assessing the Security Benefits of Cloud Computing&#34;</title>
      <link>http://zhen.org/blog/response-to-assessing-the-security-benefits-of-cloud-computing/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2008 01:58:22 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://zhen.org/blog/response-to-assessing-the-security-benefits-of-cloud-computing/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Craig Balding from &lt;a href=&#34;http://cloudsecurity.org&#34;&gt;Cloud Security&lt;/a&gt; wrote an interesting piece on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://cloudsecurity.org/2008/07/21/assessing-the-security-benefits-of-cloud-computing/&#34;&gt;security benefits of cloud computing&lt;/a&gt; back in July (that I just now got to read.) Craig qualified the post as &lt;strong&gt;potential security benefits&lt;/strong&gt; of Cloud Computing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After reading through it, I felt compelled to respond, even though it&amp;rsquo;s a been over a month since the post is up. Craig mentioned he won&amp;rsquo;t talk about the &amp;ldquo;flip&amp;rdquo; side of these benefits in this post, so I figure I will do that. :)
I have only quoted the headers from Craig&amp;rsquo;s article so please refer to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://cloudsecurity.org/2008/07/21/assessing-the-security-benefits-of-cloud-computing/&#34;&gt;original article&lt;/a&gt; for all the details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, Craig has made a good list of potential benefits. However, we really need to distinguish the benefits of virtualization vs cloud computing. Many of the benefits listed here are really benefits of virtualization and not cloud computing. When I read the title, I was hoping to read about how the cloud could be more secure than enterprise environments. I think this list has a mix of that, and how enterprise could use the cloud for some security use cases. That&amp;rsquo;s fine but mixing them together can be misleading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;1-centralised-data:6f40eb59ee53d3eb29452a51daa15d4e&#34;&gt;1. Centralised Data&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reduced Data Leakage&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Craig said, &amp;ldquo;this is the benefit I hear most from Cloud providers&amp;rdquo;. Unfortunately I have to disagree with Craig here. In my view, the cloud providers are dead wrong about this one. Many of the cloud providers talk about how laptops or backup tapes being stolen as the biggest threat to data leakage, and they are right about that. However, having enterprise data stored in the cloud doesn&amp;rsquo;t reduce these risks one bit. Travelers will continue to copy data to their laptops as they need to access them while on the road. Old habits die hard. Enterprises will continue to backup data to tapes because they can&amp;rsquo;t simply reply on cloud providers to backup their data. These will still happen no matter where the data is stored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, there likely will be an increased chance of data leakage by using cloud computing because now the cloud providers will have to somehow backup their data (maybe on tape!!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Monitoring benefits&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most enterprises, probably including the one Craig works for, have centralized file servers, content management systems, etc etc. However, we continue to see problems with data leakage. Having data stored in clouds is not all that different than storing on centralized corporate file servers. Centralized storage and monitoring is not an advantage for clouds. Enterprises had centralized storage/archiving solutions for years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my opinion, cloud storage makes it even tougher to monitor data leakage. Think about the tools available to monitor enterprise file servers. Many of them monitors all types of access: read, write, via CIFS/NFS/etc, via local system. How do you do all of that in the cloud? Think S3, the only thing S3 provide you are http access logs. You have no way of knowing who else viewed your files if it&amp;rsquo;s done locally, for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;2-incident-response-forensics:6f40eb59ee53d3eb29452a51daa15d4e&#34;&gt;2. Incident Response / Forensics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Forensic readiness&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To a certain extent this benefits is real. However, it&amp;rsquo;s not a cloud-only benefit. You get the same benefit by simply doing virtualization on your infrastructure. VMware allows you to easily clone an image so that you can perform whatever analysis is needed on the image instead of the original virtual machine. Same as Xen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, think about the cases where forensics require physical hard disk scan in case the attacker has &amp;ldquo;rm&amp;rdquo; the &amp;ldquo;bad stuff&amp;rdquo; such as audit trails or root kit. You now have NO WAY of getting to that in a virtualized environment. Granted, this is probably an issue with any network/san attached storage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Decrease evidence acquisition time&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Same as above, it&amp;rsquo;s not a cloud-exclusive benefit. It&amp;rsquo;s simply a benefit of virtualization. The only real benefit of the cloud, as mentioned by Craig, is not having to &amp;ldquo;find&amp;rdquo; storage. Though I would say that&amp;rsquo;s the least of your worries if there&amp;rsquo;s a real attack that happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Eliminate or reduce service downtime&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, if the server/VM is truly &amp;ldquo;0wn3d&amp;rdquo;, I am not sure you want to keep that system up and running. You may want to bring a good copy of the VM up and run that instead. (or just go back to a previous good snapshot.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, with the cloud, you don&amp;rsquo;t even have a CHOICE of using physical acquisition toolkit. So I am not so sure that&amp;rsquo;s a benefit. :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Decrease evidence transfer time&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, not a real benefit of the cloud. First, bit-by-bit copies of the VM in the cloud still takes time just like if you would in the real world. Second, this benefit can also be realized as part of the internal VM infrastructure, not cloud-exclusive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Eliminate forensic image verification time&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, so this is a minor benefit, but not a security benefit of the cloud. It&amp;rsquo;s more about the performance and scalability of the cloud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Decrease time to access protected documents&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both this and the next benefit are really about the elasticity and scalability of the clouds and not security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;3-password-assurance-testing-aka-cracking:6f40eb59ee53d3eb29452a51daa15d4e&#34;&gt;3. Password assurance testing (aka cracking)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Decrease password cracking time&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Same as above, this is about the benefits of elasticity and scalability, not security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keep cracking activities to dedicated machines&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Same as above, this is about the benefits of elasticity and scalability, not security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;4-logging:6f40eb59ee53d3eb29452a51daa15d4e&#34;&gt;4. Logging&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;‘Unlimited’, pay per drink storage&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Improve log indexing and search&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Getting compliant with Extended logging&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, this is about the utility and scalability of the cloud. Not a cloud security benefit. It&amp;rsquo;s about using the cloud for security tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;5-improve-the-state-of-security-software-performance:6f40eb59ee53d3eb29452a51daa15d4e&#34;&gt;5. Improve the state of security software (performance)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Drive vendors to create more efficient security software&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe this is true for even software on dedicated machines. Not cloud-exclusive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;6-secure-builds:6f40eb59ee53d3eb29452a51daa15d4e&#34;&gt;6. Secure builds&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pre-hardened, change control builds&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This I agree with. Having pre-built images that are secure from the start is a HUGE benefit. Though it&amp;rsquo;s a benefit of virtualization and virtual machines, not cloud-exclusive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reduce exposure through patching offline&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t understand this one. Once the VM is running in production, I can imagine taking that down to do patching. You would have to manage the patching process like any other machine, no?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now image templates can be updated with patches so if new machines are started, they are pre-patched.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Easier to test impact of security changes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again I agree. However, it&amp;rsquo;s still the benefit of virtualization, not necessarily cloud-exclusive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;7-security-testing:6f40eb59ee53d3eb29452a51daa15d4e&#34;&gt;7. Security Testing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**Reduce cost of testing security: **&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Agreed. It&amp;rsquo;s a side benefit of economies of scale.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>